Finding Aid for Emil Weddige Papers 1916-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Emil Weddige Papers 1916-1999, 1985-1998
Weddige, Emil, 1907-
1 linear foot and 1 oversize folder
Lithographer, professor of art at the University of Michigan. Exhibition catalogs, publications containing reproductions of his work, pricelists, miscellaneous correspondence and clippings; and photographs.
93343 Aa 2 UA1
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was the gift of the Weddige estate (donor no. 8040 ) and came to the library in 2001.
The collection is open for research.
Emil Albert Weddige was born in 1907 in Sandwich, Ontario, Canada to American parents of French, German and Windot Indian (Native American) background. He received a bachelor's degree from Eastern Michigan University in 1934, and later studied under Morris Kantor at the Art Students League, New York, and under Emil Ganse in Woodstock, New York. In 1937 he served as a Teaching Fellow at the University of Michigan, where he received a Master of Design degree (1937) and was appointed Instructor. In 1949 he established a second studio in Paris, France. In 1957 the University of Michigan appointed him Professor of Art. In 1974 the University of Michigan appointed him Professor Emeritus, and Eastern Michigan University bestowed an honorary degree of Doctor of Fine Arts upon him.
An internationally prominent lithographer, Weddige had more than 100 one-man exhibitions in the United States and Europe, received more than 25 major awards, and published a book on his technique, Lithography (1966). Weddige's work is in the permanent collections of more than a dozen museums, including the National Gallery of Art in Washington, DC, the Smithsonian institution, the Library of Congress, the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York, and the Chicago Art Institute. His lithographs also appear in public buildings throughout the U.S., Europe and Japan.
The Weddige papers consist of various materials documenting his personal and professional life. Included are exhibition catalogs and reproductions of Weddige's work appearing on greeting cards and other publications. There are also many photographs of Weddige at work in his studio, at exhibitions, and with friends and family. The bulk of the documents relates to the period of 1985 to 1999. A small portion of the collection dates from his childhood and high school years.
Printmaking.; Weddige, Emil, 1907-
Subjects - Visual Material:
Angell Hall (University of Michigan)-- In art.; First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Liberty Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.) -- In art.; Michigan--In art.; Stein Road (Ann Arbor, Mich.: Township) -- In art.; Whitefish Point (Mich.) -- In art.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Presses.; Lithographs.; Posters.
- Professional Life and Artwork, 1950-1998
  - Artrain (invitation to event honoring Weddige; also progress report), 1999 (Box 1)
  - Christmas cards and notecards designed by Weddige (Box 1)
  - Donations and art for charity, 1985, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Exhibitions, 1950-1998
    - Catalogues and pricelists, 1950-1998 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1955-1998 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1998 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous artwork (includes notebook) (Box 1)
  - Publications with Weddige lithographs, 1958, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Reproductions of artwork (Box 1)
  - Weddige Fellowship (drafts), 1998 (Box 1)
  - WKAR-TV (Michigan State University) documentary (clippings), 1985 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Paris studio (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (includes exhibitions, lithographs and lithography process), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Slides
    - Artwork (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (includes lithography process and work of other artists), 1962, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous and Personal, 1916-1996
  - Correspondence and notes
    - Childhood, 1916-1926 (Box 1)
    - Adulthood, 1992-1998 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966-1999 (Box 1)
  - Writings, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    (also in oversize folder UAl)
    - Early 20th century photographs (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Photograph album containing photographs related to event at the Detroit Institute of Art (Box 1)
  - Lithographs (Folder UAl)
    (oversize folder UAl)